<chapter id="biblio">

<title>Bibliography</title>
<para>
Most of the information in this book has been extracted from the kernel
documentation and source code.  This is the best place for information on
how to build and install the kernel, and is usually kept up to date when
things in the build procedure change.
</para>


<sect1>

<title>Books</title>

<para>
There are a number of very good Linux kernel programming books availble,
but only a few that deal with building and installing the kernel.  Here is
a list of books that the author has found useful when dealing with the
Linux kernel.
</para>

<sect2>
<title>General Linux Books</title>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
Ellen Siever, Aaron Weber, Stephen Figgins, Robert Love, Arnold Robbins.
<emphasis>Linux in a Nutshell, Fifth Edition</emphasis>.
O'Reilly &amp; Associates, 2005
</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This book can be has the most complete and authoritative command reference
for Linux.  It covers almost every different command that you will ever
need to use.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

<para> ldd3 stuff below FIXME!!!
</para>

</sect2>



<sect2>
<title>Linux Kernel Books</title>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>Love, Robert.  <emphasis>Linux Kernel Development</emphasis>.  Sam's
Publishing, 2004.</term>
<listitem><para>
Robert Love's book covers Linux kernel programming with a broad scope.  It
is a reference which should be on every Linux hacker's bookshelf.
</para>
</listitem></varlistentry>


<varlistentry>
<term>Bovet, Daniel P. and Cesate, Marco.  <emphasis>Understanding the
Linux Kernel, Second Edition</emphasis>.  O'Reilly &amp; Associates,
2003.</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This book covers the design and implementation of the Linux kernel in
great detail. It is more oriented toward providing an understanding
of the algorithms used than documenting the kernel API.  This book covers
the 2.4 kernel, but still contains a great deal of useful information.
</para></listitem></varlistentry>


<varlistentry>
<term>Yaghmour, Karim.  <emphasis>Building Embedded Systems</emphasis>.
O'Reilly &amp; Associates,  2003.</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This book will be useful for people writing Linux code for embedded
systems.  
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Gorman, Mel.  <emphasis>Understanding the Linux Virtual Memory
Manager</emphasis>.  Prentice Hall PTR, 2004.</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Developers wanting to know more about the Linux virtual memory subsystem
may wish to have a look at this book.  It is centered around the 2.4
kernel, but contains 2.6 information is well.  
</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Unix Design and Internals</title>

<variablelist>

<varlistentry>
<term>Bach, Maurice.  <emphasis>The Design of the Unix Operating
System</emphasis>. Prentice Hall. 1987.</term>
<listitem>
<para>
This book, though quite old, covers all the issues related to Unix
implementations. It was the main source of inspiration for Linus in the
first Linux versions.
</para>
</listitem></varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Stevens, Richard.  <emphasis>Advanced Programming in the UNIX
Environment</emphasis>.  Addison-Wesley, 1992.</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Every detail of Unix system calls is described herein, which is a good
companion when implementing advanced features in the device methods.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term>Stevens, Richard.  <emphasis>Unix Network Programming</emphasis>.
Prentice Hall PTR, 1990.</term>
<listitem>
<para>
Perhaps the definitive book on the Unix network programming API.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Web sites</title>

<para>
In the fast-moving world of Linux kernel development, the most current
information is often found online.  The following is our selection of the
best web sites as of this writing.  
</para>

<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term><systemitem role="url">http://www.kernel.org</systemitem></term><term><systemitem role="url">ftp://ftp.kernel.org</systemitem></term>
<listitem>
<para>
This site is the home of Linux kernel development. You'll find the
latest kernel release and related information. Note that the FTP site
is mirrored throughout the world, so you'll most likely find a mirror
near you.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>


<varlistentry>
<term><systemitem role="url">http://www.bkbits.net</systemitem></term>
<listitem>
<para>
This site hosts the source repositories used by a number of prominent
kernel developers.  The project called ``linus'', in particular, contains
the mainline kernel as maintained by Linus Torvalds.  If you are curious
about the very latest patches which have been applied to the kernel, this
is the place to look.
</para>
</listitem></varlistentry>


<varlistentry>
<term><systemitem role="url">http://www.tldp.org</systemitem></term>
<listitem>
<para>
<indexterm><primary>Linux Documentation Project web site</primary></indexterm>
The Linux Documentation Project carries a lot of interesting documents
called "HOWTOs"; some of them are pretty technical and cover
kernel-related topics.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>


<varlistentry>
<term><systemitem role="url">http://www.linux.it/kerneldocs</systemitem></term>
<listitem>
<para>
This page contains many kernel-oriented magazine articles written by
Alessandro. Some of them date back a few years but they usually still apply;
some of them are in Italian, but usually an English translation
is available as well.
<!-- not yet, but I'm investing some time or bucks to do that for
the whole series of new articles -->
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><systemitem role="url">http://lwn.net</systemitem></term>
<listitem>
<para>
At the risk of seeming self-serving, we'll point out this news site
(edited by one of your authors) which, among other things, offers
regular kernel development coverage and API change information.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><systemitem role="url">http://www.kerneltraffic.org</systemitem></term>
<listitem>
<para>
Kernel Traffic is a popular site that provides weekly summaries of
discussions on the Linux kernel development mailing list.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

<varlistentry>
<term><systemitem role="url">http://www.kerneltrap.org/</systemitem></term>
<listitem>
<para>
This site picks up occasional interesting developments in the Linux and BSD
kernel communities.
</para>
</listitem></varlistentry>


<varlistentry>
<term><systemitem role="url">http://www.kernelnewbies.org</systemitem></term>
<listitem>
<para>
This site is oriented toward new kernel developers. There is beginning
information, an FAQ, and an associated IRC channel for those looking
for immediate assistance.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>


<varlistentry>
<term><systemitem role="url">http://janitor.kernelnewbies.org/</systemitem></term>
<listitem>
<para>
The Kernel Janitors project is the place where new kernel programmers can
learn how to join into the development effort.  A wide range of small,
generally simple tasks that need to be done all over the kernel are
described here.  There is a mailing list that helps new developers get
these changes into the main kernel tree.  This is a great place for anyone
wanting to start doing Linux kernel development, but not knowing where to
begin.
</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>

</variablelist>


</sect1>
</chapter>
