<!--<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">-->
<chapter id="LKN-command-line">

<title>Kernel boot command line reference
<footnote>
<para>
The majority of this chapter is based on the in-kernel documentation for the
different kernel boot command line reference options, which were written by the
kernel developers and released under the GPL.
</para>
</footnote>
</title>


<para>
The kernel has a wide variety of different command line options that are
able to control lots of different actions.  This chapter documents the
majority of them, breaking them down into different logical sections.  A
number of architecture specific and individual driver options are not
listed here.  For a complete list of all known options, please see the
kernel file, <filename>Documentation/kernel-parameters.txt</filename>
and the individual architecture specific documentation files.
</para>

<para>
Along with all of the different options show here, all modules
paramaters are able to be passed on the command line also, if the module
is built into the kernel image.  For example, the
<literal>usbcore</literal> module accepts the paramater
<literal>blinkenlights</literal> as an option to display flashing lights
on all supported USB 2.0 hubs (don't ever say the kernel developers
don't have a sense of humor.)  Normally, when loading a module, to set
this paramater you would do:
<screen>
$ <userinput>modprobe usbcore blinkenlights=1</userinput>
</screen>
But if the <literal>usbcore</literal> module is built into the kernel,
you need to use the modulename, with a <literal>.</literal> to specify
the option:
<screen>
usbcore.blinkenlights=1
</screen>
</para>

<para>
Module options for modules that are built into the kernel are also
allowed to be changed at run time by looking in the
<filename>/sys/module/</filename> directory for the specified module
desired.
</para>

<para>
Note that not all of the listed options are always available, the
majority of them depend on a kernel configuration option that builds the
subsystem into the kernel, and also the presence of the specific
hardware.
</para>

<para>
Note that all of these paramaters are case sensitive.
</para>


<sect1>
<title>Example options</title>

<!--
<reference>  not sure this is necessary -->

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>nousb</refname>
    <refpurpose>Disable the USB subsystem</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	requires
	<literal>USB</literal>
	</para>

	<para>
	If this command line option is present, the USB subsystem will not be
	initialized.
	</para>

</refsect1>
</refentry>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>mem</refname>
    <refpurpose/>  <!-- not provided -->
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para><literal>mem=</literal><emphasis>nn</emphasis>[<replaceable>KMG</replaceable>]</para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	Force a specified amount of memory to be used by the
	kernel. <emphasis>nn</emphasis> is measured in units of... [Is
	this one of those k, m, g-modified values?]
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Options not requiring hardware</title>

<para>
These options should always be available, and not depend on any specific
subsystem or hardware being present in the system in order to work
properly.
</para>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>apic</refname>
    <refpurpose>Change the output verbosity of the APIC subsystem when booting</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para><literal>apic=</literal>[<replaceable>quiet</replaceable>(default)|<replaceable>verbose</replaceable>|<replaceable>debug</replaceable>]</para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	This option changes how verbose the APIC subsystem is when booting
	the kernel.
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>cachesize</refname>
    <refpurpose>Override the level 2 CPU cache size detection by the kernel.</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para><literal>cachesize=</literal><emphasis>nn</emphasis></para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	Sometimes CPU hardware bugs make them report the cache size
	incorrectly. The kernel will attempt to work around and fix known
	problems with most CPUs, but for some CPUs it is not possible to
	determine what the correct size should be.  This option provides an
	override for these situations.
	<emphasis>nn</emphasis> is measured in units of bytes.
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

<screen>
console=
	Output console device and options.

	tty[n]	Use the virtual console device [n].

	ttyS[n][,options]
	ttyUSB0[,options]
		Use the specified serial port.  The options are of
		the form "bbbbpnf", where "bbbb" is the baud rate,
		"p" is parity ("n", "o", or "e"), "n" is number of
		bits, and "f" is flow control ("r" for RTS or
		omit it).  Default is "9600n8".

		See the file
		<filename>Documentation/serial-console.txt</filename> for more
		information and the file
		<filename>Documentation/networking/netconsole.txt</filename> for an
		alternative if you do not have a serial port.

	uart,io,[addr][,options]
	uart,mmio,[addr][,options]
		Start an early, polled-mode console on the 8250/16550
		UART at the specified I/O port or MMIO address,
		switching to the matching ttyS device later.  The
		options are the same as for ttyS, above.
</screen>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>crashkernel</refname>
    <refpurpose>Reserve a portion of physical memory for kexec to use</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para><literal>crashkernel=</literal><emphasis>nn</emphasis>[<replaceable>KMG</replaceable>]@<emphasis>ss</emphasis>[<replaceable>KMG</replaceable>]</para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	The kexec subsystem likes to have a portion of physical memory to
	use.  This option reserves that memory from the rest of the kernel
	and will switch to use it if the kernel panics.
	<emphasis>nn</emphasis> specifies the amount of memory to reserve
	and is measured in units of kilo, mega, or
	gigabytes.
	<emphasis>ss</emphasis> specifies the location for this memory
	chunk and is measured in units of kilo, mega, or
	gigabytes.
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>debug</refname>
    <refpurpose>Enable kernel debugging.</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	This option will enable the kernel log level to default to the
	debug level, so that all debug messages will be printed to the
	console at boot time.
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>
    </refname>
    <refpurpose>
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para>
    <literal>apic=</literal>[<replaceable>quiet</replaceable>(default)|<replaceable>verbose</replaceable>|<replaceable>debug</replaceable>]
    </para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>dhash_entries</refname>
    <refpurpose>Set the number of dentry hash buckets.
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para>
    <literal>dhash_entries=</literal><emphasis>nn</emphasis>
    </para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	This option lets you override the default number of hash buckets
	for the kernel's dentry cache.  Only use this if you know what you
	are doing.
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>earlyprintk</refname>
    <refpurpose>Show early boot messages
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para>
    <literal>earlyprintk=</literal>[<replaceable>vga</replaceable>|<replaceable>serial</replaceable>[,<replaceable>ttyS</replaceable><emphasis>n</emphasis>[,<emphasis>baudrate</emphasis>]]]
    </para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	This option enables the ability to see the kernel log messages that
	happen before the traditional console is initialized.  It can be
	very useful for tracking down hardware issues.  Currently only the
	VGA device or the serial port will work, not both at the same time.
	Also, only the <literal>ttyS0</literal> or <literal>ttyS1</literal>
	serial devices will work.  Interaction with the standard serial
	driver is not very good, and the VGA output will eventually be
	overwritten by the real console.
	</para>
	<para>
	Append the string <literal>,keep</literal> to not disable the
	messages when the real kernel console is initializes and takes over
	the system.
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>elevator</refname>
    <refpurpose>Sets the default I/O scheduler elevator
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para>
    <literal>elevator=</literal>[<replaceable>anticipatory</replaceable>|<replaceable>cfg</replaceable>|<replaceable>deadline</replaceable>|<replaceable>noop</replaceable>]
    </para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	This sets the default I/O scheduler to be the one specified.  See
	<xref linkend="CONFIG_IOSCHED_NOOP" /> for a list of the different
	I/O schedulers available, and what they do.
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>elfcorehdr
    </refname>
    <refpurpose>Specify the start of the kernel core image elf header</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para>
    <literal>elfcorhdr=</literal><emphasis>nn</emphasis>
    </para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	This will specify the physical address that the kernel core image's
	elf header is at.  This is used by kexec to find the kernel when
	booting the secondary kernel image.  <emphasis>nn</emphasis> is a
	memory location.
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>hashdist</refname>
    <refpurpose>Distribute large hashes across NUMA nodes</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para>
    <literal>hashdist=</literal>[<replaceable>0</replaceable>|<replaceable>1</replaceable>]
    </para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	Large hashs that are allocated during the boot process are by
	default on the IA-64 platform distributed across the different NUMA
	nodes.  This option lets the user turn this option on or off.
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>highmem</refname>
    <refpurpose>Specify the size of the highmem memory zone</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para>
    <literal>highmem=</literal><emphasis>nn</emphasis>
    </para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	This option will force the highmem memory zone to have an exact
	size of <emphasis>nn</emphasis> bytes.  This will work even on
	boxes that have no highmem zones by default.  It will can also
	reduce the size of the highmem zone for machines with a lot of
	memory.
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>hugepages</refname>
    <refpurpose>Set the number of hugetlb pages</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para>
    <literal>hugepages=</literal><emphasis>nn</emphasis>
    </para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	Set the maximum number of hugetlb pages to be
	<emphasis>nn</emphasis>.
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>noirqbalance</refname>
    <refpurpose>Disable kernel irq balancing</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	This option will disable all of the built in kernel irq balancing logic.
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>ihash_entries</refname>
    <refpurpose>Set the number of inode hash buckets.
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para>
    <literal>ihash_entries=</literal><emphasis>nn</emphasis>
    </para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	This option lets you override the default number of hash buckets
	for the kernel's inode cache.  Only use this if you know what you
	are doing.
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>


<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>init</refname>
    <refpurpose>Set the program to run at init time</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para>
    <literal>init=</literal><emphasis>filename</emphasis>
    </para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	Run the specified binary as the init process instead of the default
	<filename>/sbin/init</filename> program.
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>
    </refname>
    <refpurpose>
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para>
    <literal>apic=</literal>[<replaceable>quiet</replaceable>(default)|<replaceable>verbose</replaceable>|<replaceable>debug</replaceable>]
    </para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>
<screen>
initcall_debug
	Trace initcalls as they are executed.  Useful for working out where the
	kernel is dying during startup.

initrd=
	Specify the location of the initial ramdisk

combined_mode=
	control which driver uses IDE ports in combined mode: legacy IDE
	driver, libata, or both (in the libata case, libata.atapi_enabled=1 may
	be useful as well).  Note that using the ide or libata options may
	affect your device naming (e.g. by changing hdc to sdb).
	Format: combined (default), ide, or libata

irqfixup
	When an interrupt is not handled search all handlers for it. Intended
	to get systems with badly broken firmware running.

irqpoll
	When an interrupt is not handled search all handlers for it. Also check
	all handlers each timer interrupt. Intended to get systems with badly
	broken firmware running.

isolcpus=
	Isolate CPUs from the general scheduler.
	Format: [cpu number],...,[cpu number]
	This option can be used to specify one or more CPUs to isolate from the
	general SMP balancing and scheduling algorithms. The only way to move a
	process onto or off an "isolated" CPU is via the CPU affinity syscalls.
	[cpu number] begins at 0 and the maximum value is "number of CPUs in
	system - 1".

	This option is the preferred way to isolate CPUs. The alternative -
	manually setting the CPU mask of all tasks in the system - can cause
	problems and suboptimal load balancer performance.

kstack=N
	Print N words from the kernel stack in oops dumps.

lapic
	Enable the local APIC even if BIOS disabled it.

load_ramdisk=
	List of ramdisks to load from floppy.
	See Documentation/ramdisk.txt for more information.

loglevel=
	All Kernel Messages with a loglevel smaller than the console loglevel
	will be printed to the console. It can also be changed with klogd or
	other programs. The loglevels are defined as follows:

	0 (KERN_EMERG)		system is unusable
	1 (KERN_ALERT)		action must be taken immediately
	2 (KERN_CRIT)		critical conditions
	3 (KERN_ERR)		error conditions
	4 (KERN_WARNING)	warning conditions
	5 (KERN_NOTICE)		normal but significant condition
	6 (KERN_INFO)		informational
	7 (KERN_DEBUG)		debug-level messages

log_buf_len=n
	Sets the size of the printk ring buffer, in bytes.
	Format: { n | nk | nM }
	n must be a power of two.  The default size is set in the kernel config
	file.

lpj=n
	Sets loops_per_jiffy to given constant, thus avoiding time-consuming
	boot-time autodetection (up to 250 ms per CPU). 0 enables autodetection
	(default). To determine the correct value for your kernel, boot with
	normal autodetection and see what value is printed. Note that on SMP
	systems the preset will be applied to all CPUs, which is likely to
	cause problems if your CPUs need significantly divergent settings. An
	incorrect value will cause delays in the kernel to be wrong, leading to
	unpredictable I/O errors and other breakage. Although unlikely, in the
	extreme case this might damage your hardware.

max_loop=
	Maximum number of loopback devices that can be mounted
	Format: [1-256]

maxcpus=
	Maximum number of processors that an SMP kernel should make use of.

max_addr=
	All physical memory greater than or equal to this physical address is
	ignored.

mce
	Machine Check Exception

mem=nn[KMG]
	Force usage of a specific amount of memory Amount of memory to be used
	when the kernel is not able to see the whole system memory or for test.
	[IA-32] Use together with memmap= to avoid physical address space
	collisions. Without memmap= PCI devices could be placed at addresses
	belonging to unused RAM.

mem=nopentium
	Disable usage of 4MB pages for kernel memory.

memmap=exactmap
	Enable setting of an exact E820 memory map, as specified by the user.
	Such memmap=exactmap lines can be constructed based on BIOS output or
	other requirements. See the memmap=nn@ss option description.

memmap=nn[KMG]@ss[KMG]
	Force usage of a specific region of memory Region of memory to be used,
	from ss to ss+nn.

migration_cost=
	debug: override scheduler migration costs
	Format: [level-1-usecs],[level-2-usecs],...
	This debugging option can be used to override the default scheduler
	migration cost matrix. The numbers are indexed by 'CPU domain
	distance'.
	E.g. migration_cost=1000,2000,3000 on an SMT NUMA box will set up an
	intra-core migration cost of 1 msec, an inter-core migration cost of 2
	msecs, and an inter-node migration cost of 3 msecs.

	WARNING: using the wrong values here can break scheduler performance,
	so it's only for scheduler development purposes, not production
	environments.

migration_debug=
	migration cost auto-detect verbosity
	Format=[0|1|2]
	If a system's migration matrix reported at bootup seems erroneous then
	this option can be used to increase verbosity of the detection process.
	We default to 0 (no extra messages), 1 will print some more
	information, and 2 will be really verbose (probably only useful if you
	also have a serial console attached to the system).

migration_factor=
	multiply/divide migration costs by a factor
	Format=[percent]
	This debug option can be used to proportionally increase or decrease
	the auto-detected migration costs for all entries of the migration
	matrix.  E.g. migration_factor=150 will increase migration costs by
	50%. (and thus the scheduler will be less eager migrating cache-hot
	tasks) migration_factor=80 will decrease migration costs by 20%. (thus
	the scheduler will be more eager to migrate tasks)

	WARNING: using the wrong values here can break scheduler performance,
	so it's only for scheduler development purposes, not production
	environments.

nmi_watchdog=
	Debugging features for SMP kernels

no387
	Tells the kernel to use the 387 maths emulation library even if a 387
	maths coprocessor is present.

noapic
	Tells the kernel to not make use of any IOAPICs that may be present in
	the system.

noexec
	noexec=on: enable non-executable mappings (default)
	noexec=off: disable nn-executable mappings

nofxsr
	Disables x86 floating point extended register save and restore. The
	kernel will only save legacy floating-point registers on task switch.

no-hlt
	Tells the kernel that the hlt instruction doesn't work correctly and
	not to use it.

noirqdebug
	Disables the code which attempts to detect and disable unhandled
	interrupt sources.

noisapnp
	Disables ISA PnP code.

noinitrd
	Tells the kernel not to load any configured initial RAM disk.

nolapic
	Do not enable or use the local APIC.

nomce
	Machine Check Exception

noresume
	Disables resume and restores original swap space.

nosep
	Disables x86 SYSENTER/SYSEXIT support.

nosmp
	Tells an SMP kernel to act as a UP kernel.

notsc
	Disable Time Stamp Counter

panic=
	Kernel behaviour on panic
	Format: [timeout]

pause_on_oops=
	Halt all CPUs after the first oops has been printed for the specified
	number of seconds.  This is to be used if your oopses keep scrolling
	off the screen.

pnpbios=
	{ on | off | curr | res | no-curr | no-res }

pnp_reserve_irq=
	Exclude IRQs for the autoconfiguration

pnp_reserve_dma=
	Exclude DMAs for the autoconfiguration

pnp_reserve_io=
	Exclude I/O ports for the autoconfiguration Ranges are in pairs (I/O
	port base and size).

pnp_reserve_mem=
	Exclude memory regions for the autoconfiguration.
	Ranges are in pairs (memory base and size).

profile=
	Enable kernel profiling via /proc/profile
	Format: [schedule,][number]
	Param: "schedule" - profile schedule points.
	Param: [number] - step/bucket size as a power of 2 for statistical time based profiling.

prompt_ramdisk=
	List of RAM disks to prompt for floppy disk before loading.
	See Documentation/ramdisk.txt.

quiet=
	Disable log messages

ramdisk=
	Sizes of RAM disks in kilobytes [deprecated]
	See Documentation/ramdisk.txt.

ramdisk_blocksize=
	See Documentation/ramdisk.txt.

ramdisk_size=
	Sizes of RAM disks in kilobytes
	New name for the ramdisk parameter.
	See Documentation/ramdisk.txt.

rcu.blimit=
	Set maximum number of finished RCU callbacks to process in one batch.

rcu.qhimark=
	Set threshold of queued RCU callbacks over which batch limiting is
	disabled.

rcu.qlowmark=
	Set threshold of queued RCU callbacks below which batch limiting is
	re-enabled.

rcu.rsinterval=
	Set the number of additional RCU callbacks to queued before forcing
	reschedule on all cpus.

rdinit=
	Format: [full_path]
	Run specified binary instead of /init from the ramdisk,
	used for early userspace startup. See initrd.

reserve=
	Force the kernel to ignore some iomem area

resume=
	Specify the partition device for software suspend

ro
	Mount root device read-only on boot

root=
	Root filesystem

rootdelay=
	Delay (in seconds) to pause before attempting to mount the root
	filesystem

rootflags=
	Set root filesystem mount option string

rootfstype=
	Set root filesystem type

rw
	Mount root device read-write on boot

S
	Run init in single mode

time
	Show timing data prefixed to each printk message line

vdso=
	vdso=1: enable VDSO (default)
	vdso=0: disable VDSO mapping

vga=
	Select a particular video mode
	See Documentation/i386/boot.txt and Documentation/svga.txt.
	Use vga=ask for menu.
	This is actually a boot loader parameter; the value is passed to the
	kernel using a special protocol.

vmalloc=nn[KMG]
	Forces the vmalloc area to have an exact size of [nn]. This can be used
	to increase the minimum size (128MB on x86). It can also be used to
	decrease the size and leave more room for directly mapped kernel RAM.

norandmaps
	on't use address space randomization
	Equivalent to echo 0 > /proc/sys/kernel/randomize_va_space

</screen>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>ACPI options</title>

<para>
These options specify different paramaters the ACPI subsystem can use.
</para>

<screen>
acpi=
	Advanced Configuration and Power Interface
	Format: { force | off | ht | strict | noirq }
	force -- enable ACPI if default was off
	off -- disable ACPI if default was on
	noirq -- do not use ACPI for IRQ routing
	ht -- run only enough ACPI to enable Hyper Threading
	strict -- Be less tolerant of platforms that are not strictly ACPI specification compliant.
	See also Documentation/pm.txt, pci=noacpi

acpi_sleep=
	Sleep options
	Format: { s3_bios, s3_mode }
	See Documentation/power/video.txt

acpi_sci=
	ACPI System Control Interrupt trigger mode
	Format: { level | edge | high | low }

acpi_irq_balance
	ACPI will balance active IRQs
	default in APIC mode

acpi_irq_nobalance
	ACPI will not move active IRQs (default)
	default in PIC mode

acpi_irq_pci=
	If irq_balance, clear listed IRQs for use by PCI
	Format: [irq],[irq]...

acpi_irq_isa=
	If irq_balance, mark listed IRQs used by ISA
	Format: [irq],[irq]...

acpi_os_name=
	Tell ACPI BIOS the name of the OS
	Format: To spoof as Windows 98: ="Microsoft Windows"

acpi_osi=
	empty param disables _OSI

acpi_serialize
	force serialization of AML methods

acpi_skip_timer_override
	Recognize and ignore IRQ0/pin2 Interrupt Override.
	For broken nForce2 BIOS resulting in XT-PIC timer.

acpi_dbg_layer=
	Format: [int]
	Each bit of the [int] indicates an ACPI debug layer,
	Format: 1: enable, 0: disable.
	It is useful for boot time debugging. After system has booted up, it can be set via the <filename>/proc/acpi/debug_layer</filename> file.

acpi_fake_ecdt
	Workaround failure due to BIOS lacking ECDT

acpi_generic_hotkey
	Allow consolidated generic hotkey driver to override platform specific driver.
	See also Documentation/acpi-hotkey.txt.

acpi_pm_good
	Override the pmtimer bug detection: force the kernel
	to assume that this machine's pmtimer latches its value
	and always returns good values.

ec_intr=
	ACPI Embedded Controller interrupt mode
	Format: [int]
	0: polling mode
	non-0: interrupt mode (default)

memmap=nn[KMG]#ss[KMG]
	Mark specific memory as ACPI data.
	Region of memory to be used, from ss to ss+nn.

memmap=nn[KMG]$ss[KMG]
	Mark specific memory as reserved.
	Region of memory to be used, from ss to ss+nn.

pnpacpi=
	{ off }

processor.max_cstate=
	Limit processor to maximum C-state
	max_cstate=9 overrides any DMI blacklist limit.

processor.nocst
	Ignore the _CST method to determine C-states,
	instead using the legacy FADT method


</screen>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>SCSI options</title>

<para>
These options specify different paramaters the SCSI subsystem can use.
There are a number of SCSI driver specific options that are also
availble, please see the different driver documentation files in the
kernel directory, <filename>Documentation/scsi/</filename> for details
on these.
</para>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>max_luns</refname>
    <refpurpose>The maximum number of SCSI LUNS to probe</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para>
    <literal>max_luns=</literal><emphasis>nn</emphasis>
    </para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	Specifies the maximum number of SCSI LUNS that the system should
	probe.  <emphasis>nn</emphasis> is a number between 1 and
	4294967295.
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>max_report_luns</refname>
    <refpurpose>The maximum number of SCSI LUNS received</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para>
    <literal>max_report_luns=</literal><emphasis>nn</emphasis>
    </para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	Specifies the maximum number of SCSI LUNs that the system can
	receive.  <emphasis>nn</emphasis> is a number between 1 and 16384.
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>scsi_dev_flags</refname>
    <refpurpose>SCSI black/white list</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para>
    <literal>scsi_dev_flags=</literal><emphasis>vendor</emphasis><literal>:</literal><emphasis>model</emphasis><literal>:</literal><emphasis>flags</emphasis>
    </para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	This option lets the user add entries to the SCSI black/white list
	for a specific vendor and model of device.
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

</sect1>


<sect1>
<title>PCI options</title>

<para>
These options specify different paramaters the PCI subsystem can use.
</para>


<screen>

pci=option[,option...]
	These are all various PCI subsystem options:

	off
		Do not probe for the PCI bus.

	bios
		Force the use of the PCI BIOS by not accessing the hardware
		directly.  This means that the kernel should trust the BIOS,
		which is not the standard thing to do (as BIOSes are known to
		lie more than they are known to be valid.)  Use this only if
		your machine has a non-standard PCI host bridge and the normal
		boot method is not working properly.

	nobios
		Do not use the PCI BIOS but rather access the hardware directly
		instead.  This is the default method of probing for PCI devices
		in all kernels after 2.6.13.

	conf1
		Force use of PCI Configuration Mechanism 1 (a way to access PCI
		memory on i386 machines.)

	conf2
		Force use of PCI Configuration Mechanism 2 (a way to access PCI
		memory on i386 machines.)

	nommconf
		Disable use of the ACPI MMCONFIG table for PCI configuration.

	nomsi
		If the PCI_MSI kernel config parameter is enabled, this kernel
		boot option can be used to disable the use of MSI interrupts
		system-wide.

	nosort
		Do not sort PCI devices according to order given by the PCI
		BIOS. This sorting is done to get a device order compatible
		with much older kernel versions.

	biosirq
		Use PCI BIOS calls to get the interrupt routing table. These
		calls are known to be buggy on several machines and they hang
		the machine when used, but on other computers it's the only way
		to get the interrupt routing table. Try this option if the
		kernel is unable to allocate IRQs or discover secondary PCI
		buses on your motherboard.

	rom
		Assign address space to expansion ROMs.  Use this with caution
		as certain devices share address decoders between ROMs and
		other resources.

	irqmask=0xMMMM
		Set a bit mask of IRQs allowed to be assigned automatically to
		PCI devices. You can make the kernel exclude IRQs of your ISA
		cards this way.

	pirqaddr=0xAAAAA
		Specify the physical address of the PIRQ table (normally
		generated by the BIOS) if it is outside the F0000h-100000h
		range.

	lastbus=N
		Scan all buses thru bus #N. Can be useful if the kernel is
		unable to find your secondary buses and you want to tell it
		explicitly which ones they are.

	assign-busses
		Always assign all PCI bus numbers ourselves, overriding
		whatever the firmware may have done.

	usepirqmask
		Honor the possible IRQ mask stored in the BIOS $PIR table. This
		is needed on some systems with broken BIOSes, notably some HP
		Pavilion N5400 and Omnibook XE3 notebooks. This will have no
		effect if ACPI IRQ routing is enabled.

	noacpi
		Do not use ACPI for IRQ routing or for PCI scanning.

	routeirq
		Do IRQ routing for all PCI devices.  This is normally done in
		<literal>pci_enable_device()</literal>, so this option is a
		temporary workaround for broken drivers that don't call it.

	firmware
		Do not re-enumerate the bus but instead just use the
		configuration from the bootloader. This is currently used on
		IXP2000 systems where the bus has to be configured a certain
		way for adjunct CPUs.


</screen>
</sect1>


<sect1>
<title>SELinux options</title>

<para>
These options specify different paramaters the SELinux subsystem can use.
</para>

<screen>


checkreqprot=
	Set the initial checkreqprot flag value.
	Format: { "0" | "1" }
	See security/selinux/Kconfig help text.
	0 -- check protection applied by kernel (includes any implied execute protection).
	1 -- check protection requested by application.
	The default value is set via a kernel config option.
	Value can be changed at runtime via the <filename>/selinux/checkreqprot</filename> file.

enforcing=
	Set the initial enforcing status.
	Format: {"0" | "1"}
	See security/selinux/Kconfig help text.
	0 -- permissive (log only, no denials).
	1 -- enforcing (deny and log).
	Default value is 0.
	Value can be changed at runtime via the <filename>/selinux/enforce</filename> file.

selinux=
	Disable or enable SELinux at boot time.
	Format: { "0" | "1" }
	See security/selinux/Kconfig help text.
	0 -- disable.
	1 -- enable.
	Default value is set via a kernel config option.
	If enabled at boot time, the <filename>/selinux/disable</filename> file can be used later to disable prior to initial policy load.

selinux_compat_net=
	Set initial selinux_compat_net flag value.
	Format: { "0" | "1" }
	0 -- use new secmark-based packet controls
	1 -- use legacy packet controls
	Default value is 0 and is the preferred value.
	Value can be changed at runtime via the <filename>/selinux/compat_net</filename> file.

</screen>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Network options</title>

<para>
These options specify different paramaters the Networking subsystem can use.
</para>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>netdev</refname>
    <refpurpose>Set different network device paramaters.
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para>
    <emphasis><literal>netdev</literal></emphasis><literal>=</literal>[<replaceable>irq</replaceable>],[<replaceable>io</replaceable>],[<replaceable>mem_start</replaceable>],[<replaceable>mem_end</replaceable>],[<replaceable>name</replaceable>]
    </para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	Specify different network device parameters.  Note that each of these
	paramaters are specific to the different driver used by the network
	device.  These options might be documented in the different driver
	source files.
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>rhash_entries</refname>
    <refpurpose>Set the number of route cache hash buckets.
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para>
    <literal>dhash_entries=</literal><emphasis>nn</emphasis>
    </para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	This option lets you override the default number of hash buckets
	for the kernel's route cache.  Only use this if you know what you
	are doing.
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>shapers</refname>
    <refpurpose>Set the maximum number of network shapers.
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para>
    <literal>shapers=</literal><emphasis>nn</emphasis>
    </para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	This option lets you set the maximum number of network shapers that are
	possible to be used by the kernel.
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>thash_entries</refname>
    <refpurpose>Set the number of TCP connection hash buckets.
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para>
    <literal>thash_entries=</literal><emphasis>nn</emphasis>
    </para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	This option lets you override the default number of hash buckets for
	the kernel's TCP connection cache.  Only use this if you know what you
	are doing.
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

</sect1>


<sect1>
<title>NFS options</title>

<para>
These options specify different paramaters the NFS subsystem can use.
</para>

<screen>
lockd.nlm_grace_period=P
	Assign grace period.
	Format: [integer]

lockd.nlm_tcpport=N
	Assign TCP port.
	Format: [integer]

lockd.nlm_timeout=T
	Assign timeout value.
	Format: [integer]

lockd.nlm_udpport=M
	Assign UDP port.
	Format: [integer]

nfsaddrs=
	See Documentation/nfsroot.txt for full details about this option (FIXME!!!)

nfsroot=
	nfs root filesystem for disk-less boxes.
	See Documentation/nfsroot.txt for full details about this option (FIXME!!!)

nfs.callback_tcpport=
	Set the TCP port on which the NFSv4 callback channel should listen.

nfs.idmap_cache_timeout=
	Set the maximum lifetime for idmapper cache entries.

</screen>
</sect1>


<sect1>
<title>Hardware specific options</title>

<para>
These options specify different paramaters the depending on the hardware
you have present in the system.
</para>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>nousb</refname>
    <refpurpose>Disable the USB subsystem</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	If this option is present, the USB subsystem will not be initialized.
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>lp</refname>
    <refpurpose>Specify the parallel port to use and the mode of it.</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para>
    <literal>lp=</literal>[<replaceable>0</replaceable>|<replaceable>port</replaceable>[,<replaceable>port</replaceable>...]|<replaceable>reset</replaceable>|<replaceable>auto</replaceable>]
    </para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	Specify the parallel port to use.  An example of this would be
	<literal>lp=none,parport0</literal> which would not configure
	the <literal>lp0</literal> device, and the <literal>lp1</literal>
	device would use the first parallel port.
	</para>
	<para>
	If using the format, <literal>lp=port1,port2...</literal> the
	specified parallel ports would be associated with the different
	devices, starting with <literal>lp0</literal>.
	</para>
	<para>
	<literal>lp=0</literal> disables the printer driver.
	</para>
	<para>
	<literal>lp=reset</literal> causes the attached printers to be
	reset.  This option can be combined with the port specifications.
	</para>
	<para>
	<literal>lp=auto</literal> instead of a port specification list
	causes the device ids from each port will be examined by the kernel
	to determine if a IEEE 1284-compatible printer is attached.  If so,
	the kernel will manage that printer.
	</para>

</refsect1>
</refentry>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>parport</refname>
    <refpurpose>Specify the parallel port parameters</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para>
    <literal>parport=</literal>[<replaceable>0</replaceable>|<replaceable>auto</replaceable>|<replaceable>0x</replaceable><emphasis>BBBB</emphasis>[,<emphasis>IRQ</emphasis>[,<emphasis>DMA</emphasis>]]]
    </para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	This sets the parallel port driver to use these specific settings
	instead of any others.  Use <literal>auto</literal> to force the
	driver to use any IRQ/DMA settings detected (the default is to
	ignore detected IRQ/DMA settings because of possible conflicts).
	You can specify the base address, IRQ, and DMA settings;
	IRQ and DMA should be numbers, or <literal>auto</literal> (for
	using detected settings on that particular port), or
	<literal>nofifo</literal> (to avoid using a FIFO even if it is
	detected).  Parallel ports are assigned in the order they are
	specified on the command line, starting with
	<literal>parport0</literal>.
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>parport_init_mode</refname>
    <refpurpose>Configure the parallel port initialization mode</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para>
    <literal>parport_init_mode=</literal>[<replaceable>spp</replaceable>|<replaceable>ps2</replaceable>|<replaceable>epp</replaceable>|<replaceable>ecp</replaceable>|<replaceable>ecpepp</replaceable>]
    </para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	Specifies the mode that the parallel port should be operated in.
	This is necessary on the Pegasos computer where the firmware has no
	options for setting up the parallel port mode.  This function works
	for parallel port chips of type 686a and 8231.
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>nr_uarts</refname>
    <refpurpose>Maximum number of UARTs to be registered</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para>
    <literal>nr_uarts=</literal><emphasis>nn</emphasis>
    </para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	Specifies the maximum number of different UARTs that can be
	registered in the kernel.
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

</sect1>


<sect1>
<title>Timer specific options</title>

<para>
These options specify different paramaters for the timer.
</para>


<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>enable_timer_pin_1</refname>
    <refpurpose>Enable pin 1 of the APIC timer</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	This enables pin 1 of the APIC timer.  It can be useful to work
	around chipset bugs (in particular on some ATI chipsets.)  The
	kernel tries to set a reasonable default but sometimes this option
	is necessary to override it.
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>disable_timer_pin_1</refname>
    <refpurpose>Disable pin 1 of the APIC timer</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	This disables pin 1 of the APIC timer.  It can be useful to work
	around chipset bugs (in particular on some ATI chipsets.)  The
	kernel tries to set a reasonable default but sometimes this option
	is necessary to override it.
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>enable_8254_timer</refname>
    <refpurpose>Enables interrupt 0 timer routing over the 8254 chip</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	Enable interrupt 0 timer routing over the 8254 chip in addition to
	over the IO-APIC. The kernel tries to set a reasonable default but
	sometimes this option is necessary to override it.
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>disable_8254_timer</refname>
    <refpurpose>Disables interrupt 0 timer routing over the 8254 chip</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	Disable interrupt 0 timer routing over the 8254 chip in addition to
	over the IO-APIC. The kernel tries to set a reasonable default but
	sometimes this option is necessary to override it.
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>hpet</refname>
    <refpurpose>Disable HPET and use PIT instead</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para>
    <literal>hpet=disable</literal>
    </para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	This disables the HPET timer source tells the kernel to use the PIT
	timer source instead.
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>clocksource</refname>
    <refpurpose>Set the specific clocksource</refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para>
    <literal>clocksource=</literal>[<replaceable>hpet</replaceable>|<replaceable>pit</replaceable>|<replaceable>tsc</replaceable>|<replaceable>acpi_pm</replaceable>|<replaceable>cyclone</replaceable>|<replaceable>scx200_hrt</replaceable>]
    </para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	Override the default kernel clocksource and use the clocksource
	with the specified name instead.
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

<!--

template for options...

<refentry>
  <refnamediv>
    <refname>
    </refname>
    <refpurpose>
    </refpurpose>
  </refnamediv>
  <refsynopsisdiv>
    <para>
    <literal>apic=</literal>[<replaceable>quiet</replaceable>(default)|<replaceable>verbose</replaceable>|<replaceable>debug</replaceable>]
    </para>
  </refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1>
  <title>Description</title>
	<para>
	</para>
</refsect1>
</refentry>

-->


</sect1>
</chapter>
<!-- vim: set ai tw=72 : -->
